PROFESSOR: Hello, everyone,
and welcome to the content
video for graph traversal.
So we've talked about graph data
structure at an overview level.
We've talked about how do you
implement a graph as we go
from an idea to an application.
Now we're going to talk
about graph traversal, which
is I've got this big graph now.
How do I get the data out of it?
And how do I do it fast, because
there's a lot of slow ways
to get through a graph?
How do we do the fastest way?
So graph traversal and
the graph data structure
itself go hand in hand.
You need to analyze
the data structure
if you want to think about
what's the most efficient way
to traverse through the
graph to get data out of it.
So really, there's two
standards for graph traversal,
depth-first search and
breadth-first search.
Depth-first search
means you go--
you-- let me start with
breadth-first, actually.
In my opinion, it's a little
bit easier to understand.
So breadth-first is
I'm at a current node.
What are all the nodes
I can go to from here
and analyze those
or visit those next?
So if I'm at node A and
I can get to B, C, D,
I go to B, then C,
then D in that order.
So when I go to B, then
I've got the option,
well, I can go, come
back, and then go to C.
But I-- now that
I'm at B, I can just
keep going deeper and deeper
and deeper and deeper.
And that's depth-first searches.
You go to the next node,
then go to the next node,
then go to the next node
like that, whereas
breadth-first-- it's more you
keep track of where you're
at, where you've been,
and then you go to all
available nodes next together.
Here's a fun real-life
application of depth-first--
of an issue that can
come up with depth-first.
It's a funny little cartoon.
But it's actually pretty
right on with the real issue
that comes up with-- when
you do a depth-first search.
So in this cartoon, the--
this person, this guy, is
getting ready for a date.
And what are the situations
I need to be prepared for?
So three situations--
think of those like nodes,
things I need to be
prepared for as nodes--
medical emergency, dancing,
and food too expensive.
So then the next
slide or the next part
is, what kinds of
emergencies can happen?
So that's the first node here.
Well, you go down there and
think snakebite, lightning
strike, fall from chair.
Well, then breadth-first would
have said, go back and then
go to dancing next here.
But depth-first just takes
you further down that hole.
That's the common turn when
your depth-first search starts
going into places
that gets off track.
So snakebite-- then go to corn
snake, garter snake, copperhead.
And then corn snake turns
into researching snake venoms.
Research comparing snake venoms
is scattered and inconsistent.
I'll make a spreadsheet
to organize it.
And then on his date,
I'm here to pick you up.
You're not dressed.
By LD50, the inland taipan
has the deadliest venom
of any snake.
So his brain went down the hole
of medical, snakebite, and then
the corn snake and
then venoms because he
was going depth-first.
So what would a breadth-first
search look like?
You do medical emergencies
first, then dancing,
then food expensive.
Then you go deeper on medical.
What kind of medical
emergency is on there?
Then the next layer of those
emergencies, you look at those.
Then you come back and say,
what kind of dancing issues
could there be?
Then you look at those.
That's breadth-first search.
And as a fun little side
note, the inland taipan--
there's actually no human
deaths from the inland taipan
because they're very docile
and rarely, rarely bite.
But it is true that
that has the most venom.
So graph traversal--
and then so DFS and BFS,
as you probably
may have guessed,
are depth-first search
and breadth-first search.
When doing these, it's--
the real difference
is keep track of nodes
that you've visited so far.
And that's a theme
with graph traversal--
is keeping track
of the nodes you've
visited so far in a way
that's most efficient.
I'm going to skip down here.
When a node x is visited,
it's labeled and visited
and added to a tree.
If a traversal got to
a node x from node y,
y is viewed as the parent
of x and x of a child.
So again, x and y,
the parent child--
they're-- it's all really set up
to keeping track of what nodes
we visited and what nodes
we need to visit next.
Depth-first search--
so here is the steps.
They're intuitive.
But we'll just go through
them really quick.
Select an unvisited node.
Visit it and treat it
as the current node.
By the way, I'm going to throw
in a little reminder here.
How did we traverse a tree?
Remember?
It was through recursion.
So we called a
function like find,
where we gave the node we
want to go to current.left.
We call a function.
And current.left
becomes the new node.
So as we recurse down,
that's our new node.
That's the exact
same thing in graphs.
Think of it recursively.
I'm at a node.
I go to the next node.
And that's my new current node.
So that's an important
concept of the node
I've been to and my current node
because current node changes.
So we get to our
next current node,
then find an unvisited
neighbor of the current node,
visit it, and make it
the new current node.
We recurse down again to
the next current node.
And 1-- maybe this
is a good time
to bring up a
difference in trees.
Trees are-- you can
keep track of them.
You're always going
down and back up
to visit left and
right children.
Well, in graphs,
that relationship
doesn't necessarily exist.
So now another thing
to keep track of
is all of the nodes you can
visit and whether or not
they've been visited,
like an adjacency list
or an adjacency matrix.
So then you would
just have a way
to mark those nodes as
visited or unvisited
in the adjacency matrix
or the adjacency list.
And then backtrack refers
to same concept as a tree.
Once we visited, we have
to go back to the parent
to keep the traversal going.
Repeat steps 3 and 4 until
no more nodes can be found.
If there are still unvisited
nodes, repeat from step 1
and generate a forest.
So basically, just
keep recursing
until you visited everything.
That's depth-first.
Breadth-first versus
is very similar,
except now you keep
track of levels
that you've visited things.
Select an unvisited node x.
Visit it.
Have it be the root in
a BFS tree being formed.
Its level is called
the current level.
Try all in one-step
extensions of current paths
before trying larger extensions.
The extensions refer-- try
one-step extension-- that's
like the medical emergency.
Just go one level down.
Go one and the medical
emergency and look
at different
medical emergencies.
Don't go all the way down
to inland taipan venom.
Just go one step down
to medical emergencies.
Then come back and
then look at dancing.
Then step 3-- repeat
step 2 until no more
nodes can be visited.
If there are still unvisited
nodes, repeat from step 1.
That might have
sounded really wordy
and like, how am I going
to keep track of that?
It's actually pretty simple
if you make a tree out of it.
So all breadth-first
searches can
be turned into a tree, a tree
style of layers going down,
not a binary search
tree because you can
have more than one child here.
But take a look.
So here's the graph we want
to traverse that I'm circling
with my mouse right now.
Here's the tree we
can make out of it.
So we start at 0.
Well, where can I go from 0?
I can go to 1, 2, or 4.
Think of it-- that's
my next level.
Well, where can I go to from 1?
Well, 1-- I can get to 4.
But I'm already-- 4 is
already in my visited list.
It's already in
the level I'm at.
So I don't need to
keep going down there.
2-- I've got new places
to go from there.
4-- any place I can get to
from 4 I've already been to.
So there's no need
to keep adding edges
because I've
already visited it--
again, that concept
of visited nodes.
Then we go down from
here into node 2.
Node 2-- I can get
to 5, 9, and 10.
Well, what new nodes
can I get to from there?
Well, from 5, I
can go to 6, 7, 8.
9-- I can get to 11.
And from 2, I got to 10.
So breadth-first search--
and one of the pros of it
over depth-first search is it's
really nice to get a visual.
And if you're working for a
social media company where
you have tens of
millions of users,
having a nice visual
of how to traverse
it can be really useful.
We talked about breadth-first
and depth-first.
Which one's faster?
Well, it depends.
And there's actually
multiple algorithms
to traversing a graph.
Obviously, everybody's
after the same thing.
Which ones are the fastest?
Well, in slightly
different scenarios,
slightly different
types of graphs.
But there are some algorithms
that just flat out win
at the fastest--
shortest-path algorithm.
So the shortest-path
algorithm I'll show you today
is the Dijkstra's algorithm.
So one thing we need to--
one checkpoint we need
here is edge weights.
So if I think of an edge
weight like in a map,
let's say the graph
represents a map,
an edge weight could
be the distance.
So what's the shortest
distance I can drive
from here to St. George, Utah?
I'm in Logan, Utah.
From Logan, Utah,
to St. George, Utah,
what's the shortest distance?
Well, actually, I don't
know if you knew this.
You can actually jump
from Brigham City 89
and hit I-15 further south.
It's a shorter distance.
But it's less time on I-15.
So going straight to I-15 and
Brigham City and then down
is actually way faster.
But how do we know that?
Well, we know because
we probably all
tried it and people
have told their friends
and everybody knows it.
But what if you wanted
to definitively calculate
what is the shortest path?
So the edge weight there
would be the time it takes.
If-- or let's say if my goal is
to travel the shortest distance,
put the least amount of
miles on my car, that's
a little different than I
want to get to St. George
as fast as possible.
That's the least amount of time.
So if all I'm interested is the
least amount of miles on my car,
my edge weights
I'm concerned with
would be the distance of
the roads I'm driving on.
If all I care about is
getting to St. George
as fast as possible, then
the time spent on the roads
would be my edge weight.
And that would be my
shortest-path algorithm.
But same idea is I just need
to define the edge weights.
What does an edge weight mean?
And one concept we're really
not going to get into,
but it's good to be aware
of, is negative edges.
There are some graphs where
an edge has a positive value,
like in our road example.
But there could also
be a negative edge,
like calculating how much money
it takes to get from one place
to another.
It could be negative if you
have to go over a toll road.
Then that's an immediate loss of
money-- so something like that.
But we really won't get into
that negative edge weights
that much.
So Dijkstra's algorithm-- I'm
actually going to jump down to--
it's the same graph right here.
Here we go.
So Dijkstra's algorithm--
we add the edge weight
from the node to its
successor to the current node,
all nodes from collection
based on shortest distance
using a priority queue.
So Dijkstra's algorithm-- maybe
you've heard of it before.
It's actually really,
really simple.
And that's really
what, in my opinion--
what's so beautiful about it.
It's just easy-peasy.
And it will definitely
get you the shortest path.
If you want to go from
one node to another,
Dijkstra's will get
you the shortest path
and it-- faster than
other algorithms.
So here's the idea.
We're going to-- so
V0 here is our vertice
or our node, same thing.
And think of this like Logan.
And I want to know, what's
the fastest way to get
to all the other nodes in--
or all the other cities in Utah?
From V0, what's the fastest
path to all of them?
And Dijkstra's doesn't just
solve one-to-one, like V0 to V5.
It'll solve V0 to everywhere.
What Dijkstra's does
not do-- it does not
solve the shortest path from
everywhere to everywhere else.
It's just one node.
You've got to pick
a starting point.
From this starting point,
how do I get from here
to everywhere else the fastest?
That's Dijkstra's.
So there's another
algorithm to solve
how do I get from everywhere
to everywhere else the fastest.
That's called
Ford-Fulkerson, which
also handles negative weights.
So that's why
Ford-Fulkerson is popular.
We're not going to cover that.
We're just going to cover
Dijkstra's because that one's
probably the most commonly--
one you should be aware of.
Dijkstra-- so
here's how it works.
I'm going to draw it here.
So from V0, here's
the rule we follow.
What node can I get to
that's currently unvisited
for the lowest amount?
We're going for the shortest
path-- so the shortest path.
And so 1 would be my
shortest path here.
From V0, what's the
shortest path I can get to?
Well, I can get to V3 for--
at a length of 1.
I can get to V1
for a length of 2.
So my shortest path from V0
to V3 is this 1 right here.
So I'm going to draw an arc next
to it to say that's visited.
Now, here's the
beauty of Dijkstra's.
Is it possible that I could
find a shorter path to V3
later from V0?
No.
How do you know that?
Because even to get
to V1, I already
have to pay a higher cost to get
to V1 than it was to get to V3.
I got to go to cost
of 2 right there.
So even if I found an edge later
that was 0.000001 to get to V3,
I've already gone of length 2.
I already have a cost of 2.
So no matter what I find
later to get me to V3,
it'll never be
lower than V0 to V3.
And that's really--
that's the simple beauty.
I take the shortest path I
have to an unvisited node.
And I know I won't find
a shorter path later
by going to another way because
that other way is already
more expensive.
And then you just do
that over and over.
So from V0, I got to V3.
Well, for my two
visited nodes now,
what are the next
unvisited nodes
I can get to that have
the shortest path?
Well, V0 and V3--
I still can get
to V1 for cost 2.
I can get to V4 for a cost
of 3 because, remember,
I have to go through
V3, then to V4.
I can go to V6 by a cost of 5.
I can get to V5 by a cost of 9.
I can get to V2 by a cost of 3.
So the shortest path or the
lowest cost I can take right now
is V0 to V1 at a cost of 2.
And that's the
next node I visit.
And then we just do
it-- we just repeat
until we visit every node.
And that's it.
So from these three
visited nodes,
what's the next unvisited node I
can get to for the lowest cost,
for the shortest path?
Well, I can get, again,
to V2 for a cost of 3,
V4 for a cost of 3.
I can go this way
for a cost of 12.
I can go back to
V5 for a cost of 9.
I can get to V6 for a cost of 5.
And the shortest-- you
can see it's a tie--
is I can get to V2
for a cost of 3.
And I'll also do--
I'll just do the next
one right now also.
I can get to V4 for a cost of 3.
So now I visited
five of the nodes.
And the shortest cost-- the
largest cost I have so far is 3.
What's the next
one I can get to?
Well, from my currently
visited nodes-- and again,
it's all from V0.
Remember, when I calculate
path, it's from V0.
It's not I'm at V3, which is
independent of this whole thing.
V3 is a visited node.
That's part of my path from V0.
So then I do it again.
V0-- I can get to V6 for
a cost of 5 right here.
I can get to V6 if I go
this way for a cost of 9.
I can get to V5 still
for a cost of 9 this way.
I can get to V5 coming
this way from V3 to V2
and then V5 for a cost of 7.
So of all the ones available,
I know the next one
is V6 at a cost of 5.
I visit that edge.
And now that I'm
there, well, remember,
I haven't gotten to V5 yet.
But this edge-- this path I've
looked the whole time of cost 9,
9, 9--
well, now that I've gotten to
V6, I've got a cheaper option.
I can go V0 to V3 to V6
to V5 for a cost of 6.
I can come over here--
1, 2, 5-- for cost of 7
or my original one that's
been available the
whole time, a cost of 9.
And the cheapest one is
this path for a cost of 6.
All nodes have been visited.
I'm done.
Now I've given a path from
V0 to every other node.
That's the shortest path.
Dijkstra's is used
by Google Maps.
To be honest, it
uses variations.
But that's how it does it.
It figures out all the shortest
paths to the adjacent nodes
and eventually on to St. George.
So if you're thinking,
well, St. George--
do you really need to
visit all of the nodes
from Logan to St. George
to figure out the shortest
path to St. George?
No.
Again, Google Maps
uses variations.
But also remember, what
if there's an I-15 here
that's cost of 6.5?
Well, I would find it after
I'm visiting all these nodes
to St. George.
Then I'm like, that one--
let's call it the I-15 edge.
That one is cheaper
than everything.
I could guarantee it's
cheaper because I've
looked at other ways.
And that one is
the shortest path.
So that's the simplicity and
the beauty of Dijkstra's.
And then a quick
review-- so min spanning
trees-- we talked about trees
with breadth-first search.
We won't review
min spanning trees.
But I should add, though, there
are a lot of powerful Python
libraries that we use.
So you are not
going to be required
to code the traversal
algorithms themselves.
But you still need to be aware
of the concepts of visited,
unvisited, and how it works
and how it gives it its speed.
So when you do go to use
these Python libraries
that I'm going to give you
and show you how to use--
that you understand what they're
doing and when to use which one
and why one might be the best.
So that'll be it.
That concludes
this content video.
Thanks for watching.